Guide to the Camp Kinderland Records TAM.439
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Camp Kinderland Records
1924-2014, ongoing
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Camp "Kinderland" (Hopewell Junction, N.Y.)
Falk, Huey
Itzkowitz, Fay
TAM.439
30.42 Linear Feet in 3 film cans, 6 record cartons, 36 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 1 card box, 1 small flat box, and 5 flat boxes
4 websites in 4 archived websites.
62 VHS
6 CDs
4 DVD-R
2 sound tape reels
3 film reels
6 audiocassettes
10 VHS-C
6 Hi8
14.6 Gigabytes in 62 files
Camp Kinderland was founded on Sylvan Lake in Hopewell Junction, NY in 1923 by members of the Workmen's Circle who worked in the organization's New York City schools. The camp's founders sought to create a summer youth camp that would not only provide a recreational escape for the children of working people from the tenements of New York City, but also one whose culture would encourage and foster a commitment to socially progressive activism and the embracing of a rich Jewish secular tradition. The camp's founders, including some activists in the Communist Party, were associated with the left wing of the Workermen's Circle. From 1930 the Camp operated under the auspices of a branch of the International Workers order. In the 1950s, under the pressure of New York State "anti-subversive" investigations, it was incorporated independently. The collection contains administrative records (including legal and financial records, property and maintenance files, registration and membership records), files relating to Camp Kinderland's cultural programs both in and out of season, archived websites, publicity materials, oral histories, and photographic and audiovisual materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Camp Kinderland in 2008; additional materials were donated by Huey Falk in 2011 and by Fay Itzkowitz in 2013 and 2017. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2008.024, 2008.025, 2011.110, 2013.028, and 2018.001.
http://campkinderland.org/index.html and http://campkinderland.org/ were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2012-2014 as part of the Jewish American Progressive & Left Activity Web Archive. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In April 2024, https://sites.google.com/site/kinderlandstaffinfo/ and https://campkinderland.bandcamp.com/album/singing-with-ira/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2025.056.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 13 series:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1925-2006
Series II: Financial Records, 1934-1996
Series III: Property and Maintenance Records, 1933-1999
Series IV: Registration and Membership Office Records, 1953-2008
Series V: Cultural Programs, 1937-2003
Series VI: Publicity, 1947-2007
Series VII: Off-Season Programs, 1957-2009
Series VIII: 2013 Accession of Camp Kinderland Records
Series IX: Photographic Materials, 1924-2010
Series X: Audiovisual Materials, 1951-2005
Series XI: Objects, 1954-1999
Series XII: Archived Websites
Series XIII: 2017 Accretion, 1937-2014
Files are arranged alphabetically within Series I-VIII; chronologically within Series IX; and chronologically by box number within Series X-XI, with the exception of Series XIII which has not been arranged by an archivist.
Historical Note
Camp Kinderland was founded on Sylvan Lake in Hopewell Junction, NY in 1923 by members of The Workmen's Circle who worked in the organization's New York City Schools. The camp's founders sought to create a summer youth camp that would not only provide a recreational escape for the children of working people from the tenements of New York City, but also encourage and foster a commitment to socially progressive activism and the embracing of a rich Jewish secular tradition. Responding to a growing demand from parents of campers and other visitors, many of whom had already taken to sleeping on dining-hall floors, Kinderland would quickly establish an adult wing, Camp Lakeland.
Both the youth and adult camps provide summer recreation opportunities found at most camps. Recreational activities include swimming, hiking, camping and outdoor sports, as well as cultural activities such as music, drama, dance and the arts. The camp's culture is both officially and informally grounded in the Jewish tradition of progressive activism, with its core values of peace, social justice, activism, civil rights, Yiddishkeit, and friendship.
From less than one hundred campers in its first year, Camp Kinderland grew quickly, and by 1933 close to 500 children filled over thirty bungalows and tent groupings. In 1930, the leftist wing of the Workmen's Circle, along with Camp Kinderland, split off to form the International Worker's Order (IWO). The Camp was formally sponsored by the Jewish People's Fraternal Order of the IWO. Although New York State declared the IWO a "Communist-allied" organization in 1954 and revoked its charter, Camp Kinderland was able to continue by incorporating independently. Kinderland did come under scrutiny from the FBI as a Communist-affiliated organization, and its manager, David Greene, was called to testify before the House Committee on Unamerican Activites in 1955.
In 1971, after years of increasing county taxes and declining numbers of campers, the board and directors sold the Camp's property in Hopewell Junction and relocated to a rented property in Fitchville, Connecticut. After five years of renting sites for the Camp in Connecticut, Pennsylvania and New York, Kinderland purchased property in 1976 in Tolland, Massachusetts. In the same year camp was re-incorporated by the state of NY, with offices at 1 Union Square in Manhattan. Among the prominent participants in the Camp's cultural program have been Paul Robeson and Pete Seeger, and notable alumni include Chesa Boudin, Jules Dassin, Max Kellerman, Spencer Ackerman and Marisa Tomei.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains administrative records (including financial records, property and maintenance records, registration and membership records), and records relating to Camp Kinderland's cultural programs both in and out of season, archived websites, publicity materials, oral histories, and photographic and audiovisual materials. These materials document the the founding, incorporation history, physical plant, staffing and day to day operations of Camp Kinderland, at its various locations. The Camp's underlying political commitments, values and cultural programs are also documented. A number of files illustrate the Camp's reunions, and the continuing ties it maintained with several generations of former campers.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the digitized versions of the glass negatives in Boxes 44-49.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Camps -- New York (State) -- History -- 20th century.; Camps -- Massachusetts -- History -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Camps -- Pennsylvania; Financial records; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Minutes (administrative records); Songbooks.; Socialism and youth.; Jewish children -- United States.; Jewish socialists -- United States.; Suller, Elsie; Segal, Edith, 1902-; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; Camp "Kinderland" (Hopewell Junction, N.Y.); Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Falk, Huey; Itzkowitz, Fay
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1925-2011, 1.3 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Content Note
  The first series of the collection contains the camp's administrative records; Executive meeting minutes, office records, program audits, and other materials related to the running of the camp. This series includes legal records relating to New York State's investigation of Kinderland as an alleged subversive institution. Of particular interest are transcripts from the State Legislative Committee hearings conducted in 1955 with the Camp's director/instructors David Greene and Edith Segal. A copy of Kinderland's FBI file, obtained via a Freedom of Information Act request, is also in this series.
  - Administrative Meetings: Minutes, 1925-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Meetings: Minutes, 1980-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Records: Friends of Camp Kinderland Committee, Membership, 1960-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Records: General, 1926-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Records, 1956-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws and Constitution, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conferences: Annual, Administrative, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corporate Records (bound, includes Board of Director's and Administrative Committee Minutes and Audit Reports), 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Records (bound, includes Board of Director's and Executive Committee Minutes), 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Greene, David: State and Federal Investigation, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - FBI Investigation, 1955-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Itkowitz, Fay: A Brief History of Camp Kinderland, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Joint Legislative Committee to Study Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies and Organizations (NY State): General, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Joint Legislative Committee to Study Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies and Organizations (NY State): Minutes of Hearing, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Executive Board/Board of Directors, 1956-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board/Board of Directors, 1992-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Legal Records: Not-for-Profit Incorporation, 1925-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Member in Good Standing Cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Seasonal/Annual Reports: Cultural/Programmatic, 1970-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Seasonal/Annual Reports: Financial/Administrative, 1956-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II: Financial Records, 1934-1996, 0.875 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
  Series II contains financial materials, including banking records and fundraising drives conducted.
  - Camp Lakeland Inc.: Banking Records, Loans, 1941-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Camp Lakeland Inc.: Banking Records, Loans, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records: Budget, Banking, Assets, 1978-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1926-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising: Donor Correspondence, 1986-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising: General, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising: Phonathons, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ledger: Mortgage Agreement with International Workers Order; By-laws of Camp Kinderland Associates, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stock Certificate Book: New Kinderland Camp Corp. (bound), 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series III: Property and Maintenance Records, 1933-1999, 1.3 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes
  This series contains property records for the various camp sites which Kinderland called home. Together the folders provide a narrative of sorts for the camp's location over the years; its origins at Hopewell Junction's Sylvan Lake, from 1923 to 1971, the closing of that property and the inter-site years, when Kinderland spent Summers in Connecticut and Pennsylvania, and finally, the settlement of the camp at it's current home in Tolland, Massachusetts, in 1976. This series also contains maintenance records related to the physical and structural caretaking of the camp site and construction projects. In large part, this material relates to the building of a new and extensive dining hall in Tolland, beginning around 1994 and completed for use in the Summer of 1998.
  - Fitchville, CT Property, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Honesdale, PA Property, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Inter-Site Years, 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Maintenance: Audits, Projects, Proposals, and Fundraising Records, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - New Dining Hall: Equipment and Supplies Installation, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - New Dining Hall: Equipment and Supplies Installation, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - New Dining Hall: Fundraising, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - New Dining Hall: Specs, Illustrations, and Maps, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sylvan Lake/Hopewell Junction: Sale of Propertry, 1969-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sylvan Lake/Hopewell Junction: Legal, Financial, Administrative Records, 1963-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sylvan Lake: Mortgage Records (I), 1954-1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Sylvan Lake: Mortgage Records (II), 1954-1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sylvan Lake: Property Records, 1933-1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Tolland, MA: Camp Site Transition, 1976-1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Tolland, MA: Property Purchase Records, 1976-1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Registration and Membership Office Records, 1953-2010, .875 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
  Series IV contains office records for registration of campers and staff, and more general records for membership to the camp, including records of enrollment, hiring, and directories of campers. Of note is a file on the "Chris Nelson Scholarship Fund," created in memory of a camper killed in an automobile accident on his way home from camp. Beginning in the 1970s this fund was used to provide financial aid to send children to Kinderland.
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1976-1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1982-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1991-2001 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Parents, Campers, Friends, 1926-1996 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Counselor-in-Training Program, 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Directories, 1990-2003 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Directories, 2004-2010 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Nelson, Chris: Scholarship Fund, 1971-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Program Information for Parents and Campers, 1953-1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Registration, 1954-2008 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Staff Applications and Hiring, 1956-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Staff Manuals, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Staff Manuals: Non-Kinderland, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Staff Materials, 1953-1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series V: Cultural Program, 1937-2003, 2.73 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 oversized flat box
  Series V contains material and records related to Kinderland's cultural activities. Files include programs for the Olympics, a competitive athletic activity held annually in place of "color wars" or track meets. The series also includes reading materials, performance pieces and plays, song sheets, records of past projects for use by campers and staff, journals, camp-produced newsletters, trip logs, letters, records of exercises and activities, and art projects. The journal folders, which contain large sections in Yiddish, provide an intimate view of the character of the camp and the people who participated in it over the years. Also of note are reproductions of murals on various radical and labor history topics, created by Camp Kinderland campers and staff and published in the late 1990s and 2000s.
  - Camp Lakeland Program Materials, 1952-1956 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Camper Cultural Projects: Art and Murals, circa 1959-2005 (Box 9, Folder 2, Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1936-1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1955-1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1971-2001 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Cultural Program: Olympics, 1954-1981 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1937-1949 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1953-1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1969-2003 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Cultural Projects: Holocaust Commemoration, Camper Projects and Art, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Cultural Projects: Olympics Art by Campers, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Kindertog, 1937-1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Segal, Edith: Cultural Contributions, 1971-1978 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Songsheets I, 1929-1999 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Songsheets II, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Songsheets III, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Publicity, 1947-2007, 1.85 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversized flat box
  Series VI contains the records of the public face of the Camp, including its own advertisements and newsletters, as well as general media coverage of the Camp and its programs. Of note is an original pen and ink cartoon in the History folder.
  - Advertisements for Kinderland/Lakeland, 1950-1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - History, 1936-2005 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Kinderschule Graduation, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 1947-2011 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Press, 1942-1994 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Press, 1994-2006 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Public Relations: Advertising, 1967-1994 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Public Relations: Invitations/Appeals, 1967-1998 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Publicity, circa 1939-1952; cuid13648 (Box 34, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Off-season Programs, 1957-2009, 3.6 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 oversized flat box
  Series VII contains materials related to Kinderland activities, events, and programs conducted outside of the summer season. In the first part are the records of some of the Camp's many reunions, which often served as fundraisers to benefit the Camp. In these files are the records of three large reunions, held on Kinderland's 56th, 60th, and 75th anniversaries. Also in this series are the records of Kinderland cultural and recreational events; dances, protests and demonstrations, film screenings, and Passover seders among them. In addition, there are the records of benefit concerts, retirement celebrations, a trip to Cuba, and memorials organized by and for the Camp during the off-season months. Also included are various original and laser copies of posters and other graphic materials related to the camp's 75th anniversary and other events in the camp's history, possibly used for the anniversary exhibit.
  - 56th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (I), 1979 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 56th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (II), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 56th Anniversary: Program Materials (I), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 56th Anniversary: Program Materials (II), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 60th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning Records, "Biz 120" Campaign, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 60th Anniversary: Program Materials, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 75th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (I), 1999 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 75th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (II), 1999 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 75th Anniversary: Journal, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 75th Anniversary: Program Materials, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 75th Anniversary: Publicity, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 75th Anniversary: Buttons, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 75th Anniversary: Bag, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 75th Anniversary Reunion Posters, 1999; cuid13649; 1 folder (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Camp Kinderland Cookbook, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Asimolar, CA Reunion, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Camp Lakeland: Anniversaries, Reunions, Fundraising Events, 1967-1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Havana, Cuba Trip, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Klebansky, Chaike: Memorial, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Near, Holly: Benefit Concert, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Off-season Activities: General, 1954-2009 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Passover Haggadahs, 2002-2011 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Reunions, 1957-1990 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Rittel Children's Boutique (Woodstock, NY): Guest Register (photocopy), 1974-1992 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Seeger, Pete: Benefit Concert, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Seeger, Pete: Postcards, 1996-1997 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Segal, Edith: Memorial, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Suller, Elsie: Retirement Event, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Suller, Elsie: Memorial, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Undzer Zhurnal (Our Journal), 2011 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Yackle Journal, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Yackles: 60th Anniversary Reunion, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Series VIII: 2013 Accession of Camp Kinderland Records, 2003-2012, 2013.028; .4 Linear Feet 1 manuscript box
  This series contains Camp Kinderland directories from 2003, 2007, and 2012. It also contains a brochure, a 2012 Kinderland Benefit Weekend schedule, and two copies of the 2012 Kinderschule seder.
  - Directories, events and promotional materials, 2003-2013; 7 items (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Series IX: Photographic Materials, 1924-2010, 15.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 flat box, 2 oversized flat boxes, and 16 manuscript boxes; 4.18 Megabytes in 35 files
  This series primarily contains black-and-white and color photographs, slides, glass plate negatives, and photographic negatives that document camp facilities, camp activities, and the staff and campers themselves.
  - Glass Plate Negatives
    This subseries contains glass plate negatives from the summer of 1935 at Camp Kinderland, with some images from 1936. The majority of the images depict groups at the camp, many of which have no identifying information. Most of the description for the images are in Yiddish, with some English. Some significant events shown in the images include the camp's morning salute, a visit to the camp from Robert Minor, and the erection of the Lenin statue on the property.
    - Adults, 1935; cuid13391 (Box 44)
    - Arts and Crafts, 1930-1939; cuid13392 (Box 44)
    - Arts and crafts room, 1935; cuid13393 (Box 44)
    - Arts and crafts studio, 1935; cuid13394 (Box 44)
    - At the Photographers Corner, 1935; cuid13395 (Box 45)
    - At work, 1935; cuid13396 (Box 44)
    - At work, 1935; cuid13397 (Box 44)
    - Book Table, Including "The Struggle for Power" by John Stratchey, 1935; cuid13398 (Box 47)
    - Boy and Woman, 1930-1939; cuid13399 (Box 45)
    - Brothers in front of the entrance, 1935; cuid13400 (Box 44)
    - Bunk 11, Group 5, 1935; cuid13401 (Box 47)
    - Bunk 12, Group 5, 1935; cuid13402 (Box 46)
    - Bunk 13, Group 3, 1935; cuid13403 (Box 45)
    - Bunk 14, Group 4, 1935; cuid13404 (Box 46)
    - Bunk 15 (with anti-fascist posters), 1935; cuid13405 (Box 45)
    - Bunk 16, Group 4 including Pioneer Magazine, 1935; cuid13406 (Box 47)
    - Bunk 17, Workers Children Organized Banner, 1935; cuid13407 (Box 46)